Guide to the D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles archives, 1929-1995 and undated RL.00314
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles Archives
1929-1995 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles
RL.00314
152 Linear Feet
30,220 Items
The Archives document the history of Benton & Bowles advertisements; the merger of the D'Arcy MacManus Masius and Benton & Bowles companies; the early careers of William Benton and Atherton W. Hobler; research and publication about the history of Benton & Bowles; employee training, recruitment, and management; corporate publications; and marketing research. Includes material from three companies: D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles, Benton & Bowles, and D'Arcy MacManus Masius. Specific formats include memoranda; correspondence; reports; corporate publications, such as house organs, research reports, manuals, credentials, and employee reference material; press releases and a press book; speeches; clippings; photographs in color and black-and-white, and negatives; films and DVDs of advertisements; book manuscripts; audio tapes; financial papers; and a scrapbook. Clients represented in the Advertisements Series include the Procter & Gamble Company, General Foods Corporation, Allied Chemical Corporation, Avco Corporation, Colgate Palmolive Co., Florida Citrus Commission, International Business Machines Corporation, and West Point Pepperell. The unprocessed addition (554 items, dated ca. 1950s-1980s) comprises 16-mm film reels of commercials. Brand names and clients include Crest, Post cereals, Scope, Yardley, Hardees, Grape Nuts, Hasbro, and Pampers. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising, and Marketing History. (01-103).
Online Items
Selected items from this collection have been digitized and are available in: AdViews - Duke Digital Collections
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, original audiovisual materials are closed to researchers. Some use copies are available in the collection. Consult research services for further information.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles Archives were transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library by D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles in 1991 and 2001.
Historical Note
D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles
1985, Nov. Established by the merger of the Benton & Bowles and D'Arcy-MacManus and Masius advertising agencies; John S. Bowen became Chief Executive Officer; Harold Bay became President
1990 Roy J. Bostock named Chairman and CEO
Benton & Bowles
1929 William B. Benton and Chester W. Bowles opened the first office in New York City
1932 Benton & Bowles incorporated; Atherton W. Hobler became a partner in Benton & Bowles
1936 William B. Benton resigned and sold his interest in the company
1941 Chester W. Bowles resigned and sold his interest in the company; Atherton W. Hobler became President
1941-1950 Hobler served as Chairman of the Board
1948 First television copy writer, Gordon Webber, hired
1950 Hobler became Chairman of the Executive Committee
1958 First international office opened in London
1959 Broadcast Commercial Production department established with Gordon Webber as director
1967 L. T. Steele became Chairman of the Board
1968 Victor G. Bloede became President and Chief Executive Officer
1971 John S. Bowen became President and Chief Executive Officer; Victor G. Bloede became Chairman of the Board; L. T. Steele became Chairman of the Executive committee
1972 Medicus Communications established as a subsidiary company
1979 Manning, Selvage and Lee (public relations firm) acquired
1981 B&B Direct created as partner company
D'Arcy MacManus Masius
1906 D'Arcy Advertising Company founded by William Cheever D'Arcy
1971 D'Arcy-MacManus International established from merger of D'Arcy Advertising and MacManus, John & Adams
1972 D'Arcy-MacManus International and Masius, Wynne-Williams exchange stock to form D'Arcy-MacManus & Masius (known as Masius & D'Arcy-MacManus in Europe)
Collection Overview
The D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles (DMB&B) Archives consists of advertising agency records spanning the years 1929 to 1995. The bulk of the material dates from the 1950s to the mid-1980s. The Archives includes material that documents aspects of three advertising agencies: D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles (DMB&B), Benton & Bowles (B&B), and D'Arcy-MacManus & Masius (D-MM).
The Archives as a whole provides a comprehensive overview of Benton & Bowles advertisements (1932-1995) and commercials (1950s-1980s), primarily those created by the agency's New York office. Other major topics include the advertising careers of William B. Benton and Atherton W. Hobler; research and publication about the history of Benton & Bowles by Gordon Webber and Frank Smith; television programs created by B&B in the 1950s; aspects of employee training, recruitment, and management; and marketing research. The Archives also documents the merger of the D'Arcy-MacManus & Masius agency with Benton & Bowles to form DMB&B in 1985. There is very little information in the Archives about the D'Arcy-MacManus & Masius agency prior to the merger. Also, material about Benton & Bowles offices other than New York is limited, and found mostly in B&B house organs.
The D'Arcy-MacManus Masius Files comprise a very small amount of materials in the Archives. Although the D'Arcy agency had its roots in 1906, the Items gathered here date only from 1972-1985, mainly 1981 to 1985. They consist of corporate publications, notes, and clippings. The 75th Anniversary edition of Between Us contains an overview of the history of D'Arcy-MacManus & Masius, especially of the D'Arcy Advertising Company, and its clients. Profiles, a resource book, provides information on all of the divisions of the D'Arcy -MacManus Masius Worldwide group of advertising agencies.
The Benton and Bowles Files are by far the largest part of the Archives. They include primarily print advertisements (the largest series in the Archives), but also over 500 films, significant documents relating to the work of the agency, photographs, and corporate publications. The Benton & Bowles Files span the years 1929 to 1985, although most of the material dates from 1950s and after. Item types in the collection include internal memoranda; reports; speeches; printed material (manuals, leaflets, pamphlets, and house organs); photographs; research notes; credentials; employee training material; press releases and clippings; book manuscripts; audio tapes of oral history interviews; and financial papers. The Benton & Bowles Files provide documentation of the history of print and television advertising; television programming; the history of the B&B agency and its corporate culture; corporate communications; marketing research; and advertising executives.
The earliest Items in the B&B Files are two small bank books recording account activity of the fledgling agency from 1929 to 1935 and copies of William (Billie) Benton's long letters to his mother, 1929-1938, in which he confides details of his new advertising agency as well as family matters. A small number of other Items date from the 1930s and 1940s and illustrate isolated aspects of the agency's business in that period.
Long series of various agency house organs begin in 1947 and provide the most complete and continuous views of Benton & Bowles, its clients, advertising campaigns, personnel, and various offices in the U.S. and abroad.
The Advertisements Series is the largest section of the Archives and contains comprehensive files of print advertising campaigns developed mainly by Benton & Bowles from 1932-1980. The series includes primarily proofs, along with some tearsheets, of consumer and trade advertisements, most from U.S. magazines and newspapers. Files for a few clients include unusual material, such as packaging or client newsletters. Most of the advertisements were removed from large scrapbooks into which B&B employees had pasted them; many have suffered glue damage, but they remain an invaluable source for studying the development of a number of advertising campaigns over long periods of time. Longtime clients of B&B included Procter & Gamble and General Foods, among many others. Neither the Advertisements Series nor any other part of the Archives contains substantial documentation of the creative processes behind the advertisements and advertising campaigns.
For additional information about the Advertisements Series, see the data collection sheets in the Information Folders about the DMB&B Archives. The data collection sheets provide notes about: languages, other than English, used in the advertisements; countries, other than the United States, for which advertisements were produced; the use of celebrities in the advertisements; themes or social and political issues that can be studied in the advertisements; and the use of comic illustrations. The data collection sheets also note the existence of collateral literature for certain advertising campaigns. The Information Folders also contain a list of Benton & Bowles clients and the dates of agency-client relationships.
The Audiovisual Series (RESTRICTED) contains over 500 reels of 16mm film varying in lengths from 200' to 1600'. The majority of the films are compilations of commercials created mainly by Benton & Bowles for many different clients. Also included are several dozen reels of vintage television programs (shows created or sponsored by B&B), several stockholders' meetings, speeches, new business presentations, and outtakes. At the time of this writing, most of the films have not been viewed in their entirety, indexed, or reformatted. However, a selection of films has been reformatted for research use.
Addition (accession #2001-0103) (554 items, 7.5 linear ft.; dated [ca. 1950s]-[1980s]) comprises 16-mm film reels of commercials. Brand names and clients include Crest, Post cereals, Scope, Yardley, Hardees, Grape Nuts, Hasbro, and Pampers. Viewing of commercials is restricted until videocassette use copies are made. For a container list, contact Research Services.
Advertising; Advertising agencies; Advertising executives; House organs; Marketing research; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Film; DVDs; Video recordings; Negatives (photographs); John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; West Point Pepperell (Firm); Webber, Gordon; General Foods Corporation; Florida Citrus Commission; International Business Machines Corporation; Hobler, Atherton W., 1890-1974; D'Arcy MacManus Masius; D'Arcy Masius Benton & Bowles; Colgate-Palmolive Company; Avco Corporation; Allied Chemical Corporation; Benton, William, 1900-1973; Benton & Bowles; Procter & Gamble Company
- Benton & Bowles, 1929-1986 and undated, 26 boxes
  - Memoranda, 1959-1985 bulk 1970s-1981
    Scope and Contents note
    Contains records addressed to the Organization, that are usually related to the work of the entire company. It also contains Inter-office, memoranda that refer to specific individuals or groups within the organization. Materials document new partnerships between Benton & Bowles and other companies; changes in management; company directives; announcements; the results of surveys; employee activities; policies; and office operation. Announcements of new, or renewed, client accounts are also documented. Arranged alphabetically by the name of the part of the company to which the memoranda were addressed, then chronologically.
    - International, 1968-1985 (Box B&B 1)
    - Inter-Office, 1959, June,-1985, Oct (Box B&B 1)
    - Organization, 1937, Oct.-1981, 12 folders (Box B&B 1)
    - Organization, 1982-1985, 11 folders (Box B&B 2)
  - Reports, 1938-1983 bulk 1960s-1983
    Contains mostly publications and printed materials created by the Benton & Bowles Research Services and Public Relations. Some reports were distributed to clients or the general public; others were used primarily by company employees. The reports were based on research about consumer perspectives, economic conditions, or potential markets for particular products such as whiskey (1938) or frozen foods (1976). Potential markets in the new state of Alaska are described in a 1959 report. Lou Harris and Associates prepared a 1978 report about Benton & Bowles. See also oversize materials. Arranged in chronological order.
    - 1938, Congenerics in Whiskey (with accompanying map) (Box B&B 2)
    - 1958(?), Perspective: Three simple charts review our country's economic history at a glance (Box B&B 3)
    - 1959, Our 49th State: An Adventure in Marketing (Box B&B 3)
    - 1963, International Advertising, L. T. Steele (Box B&B 3)
    - 1964, A Consumer Promotion Program for Manhattan's Finest Retail Enterprises, General Public Relations (Box B&B 3)
    - 1971, Strategy Review Board (Box B&B 3)
    - 1976, The Frozen Food Industry and Growth of Baked Goods (Box B&B 3)
    - 1978, A Study of the Reputation of Benton & Bowles, Louis Harris and Associates (Box B&B 3)
    - 1979, Advertiser and Agency Reactions to Media Research Services, Research Services (Box B&B 3)
    - 1979, The Great 1979 Gasoline Shortage: Behavior & Attitudes of the American Family, Research Services (Box B&B 3)
    - 1979, A Summary of Recent Developments in the Fields of Telecommunications Law, Telecommunications Regulations, and New Technology, Media Research (Box B&B 3)
    - 1980, Men's Changing Roles in the Family of the 80s: American Consensus Report, Research Services (Box B&B 3)
    - 1981, The New TV Technologies: The View from the Viewer, An American Consensus Report, Research Services (Box B&B 3)
    - 1982, Review of Major TV Commercial Pre-Testing Research Services, Research Services (Box B&B 3)
    - 1982, Sports on Television: The Viewer Speaks Out, An American Consensus Report, Research Services (Box B&B 3)
    - 1983, The New TV Technologies; The View from the Viewer, II, An American Consensus Report, Research Services (Box B&B 4)
  - Officers and Staff, 1929-1986, undated
    Divided into four categories: Biographical Information; Speeches; Staff Resources; and Recruitment.
    - Biographical Information, 1929-1986, undated bulk 1970s-1980s
      Includes correspondence, pictures, press releases, printed material, testimony, notes, manuscripts, reprints, clippings, a scrapbook, photographs, and a press book. The section includes limited information about a few Benton & Bowles employees, except for William B. Benton and Atherton W. Hobler, who are documented more fully. The letters from Benton to his mother contain information on the early history of the company as well as on Benton's personal life. The correspondence gives a personal perspective on the early years of Benton & Bowles and chronicles financial changes, marketing strategies, personnel matters, and the general development of the company throughout the Depression of the 1930sIn the early letters, Bowles also describes his work with the Lord & Thomas agency. Additional information on Hobler and his family is in the History section. Also included is a scrapbook documenting the Crusade for Freedom, a 1950s era anti-communism activity. Arranged alphabetically by individuals' names. See also Oversize Materials.
      - Baker, William R., Jr., Press book regarding trip to Europe to study advertising industry's role in the United Kingdom and European Common Market, 1963, Jan. 19-May 31, 2 folders (Box B&B 4)
        [William R. Baker, Jr., was chairman of the Public Information Committee, New York Campaign, to establish and to fund Radio Free Europe.]
      - Benton, William B.
        - Correspondence (family), 1929-1938, 2 folders (Box B&B 4)
        - Notes and clippings, 1973, undated (Box B&B 4)
      - Bloede, Victor G.
        - 1957-1983 (Box B&B 4)
        - Pictures, 1983, undated (Box B&B 4)
      - Bowen's, John S.
        - 1974-1978 (Box B&B 4)
        - Pictures, 1978-1982, undated (Box B&B 4)
      - Bowen, John S. (Box B&B 5)
        - Pictures
          - 1978-1982, undated (Box B&B 5)
          - Family, undated (Box B&B 5)
      - Bowles, Chester W., 1986, June (Box B&B 5)
      - Goldberg, Alice, 1983 (Box B&B 5)
      - Guarascio, Philip, 1983 (Box B&B 5)
      - Hobler, Atherton W.
        - 1940-1986, undated (Box B&B 5)
        - Pictures, 1970, undated (Box B&B 5)
      - Kilborn, Helen Scofield, 1965-1981, undated (Box B&B 5)
      - Lusk, Robert, 1958-1971, undated (Box B&B 5)
      - Steele, L. T., 1946-1981, undated (Box B&B 5)
      - Webber, Gordon, 1959-1986, undated (Box B&B 5)
    - Speeches, circa 1940-1979 bulk 1965-1979
      Contains speeches given by company executives to professional associations such as the American Association of Advertising Agencies; in workshops on color advertising; at testimonial banquets; and for clients. See the Meetings section for speeches given at Benton & Bowles corporate meetings. Arranged alphabetically by speaker's name, then chronologically.
      - Bloede, Victor G. (Box B&B 5)
        - 1974, American Association of Advertising Agencies Annual Meeting (Box B&B 5)
        - 1976, International Advertising in the Mid-Seventies (Box B&B 5)
        - 1979, Response given at American Traditions Award Dinner in Honor of Victor G. Bloede (Box B&B 5)
      - Bloede, Victor G., 1983, The Advertising Man and His Social Responsibility (Box B&B 6)
      - Bowen, John S.
        - 1978, Never Having to Say You're Sorry, OR 21 Questions to Ask Before a New Product Luncheon, American Advertising Federation meeting (Box B&B 6)
        - 1979, Never Having to Say You're Sorry, OR 21 Questions to Ask Before a New Product Luncheon, Potato Chip/Snack Food Association meeting, New Orleans (Box B&B 6)
      - Guarascio, Philip, 1985, Is it Smarter to Barter? (Box B&B 6)
      - Hobler, Atherton W.
        - circa 1940-1945, Advertising and Defense (Box B&B 6)
        - 1967, The First Fifty Years are the Easiest (Box B&B 6)
      - Webber, Gordon
        - 1965, Jan., The Creative Role of the Agency Producer, presentation at Racine, Wisconsin (Box B&B 6)
        - 1965, July, The Creative Role of the Agency Producer, 8th Annual Advertising Age Creative Workshop, Chicago (Box B&B 6)
        - 1965, Nov., The Color Revolution, published in Speaking of Color, A Magazine Conference on Color (Box B&B 6)
        - 1966, The Color revolution, AAAA Western Region Conference (Box B&B 6)
        - 1967, Mar. 13, The Anatomy of the Commercial (Box B&B 6)
        - 1967, Mar. 23, The Commercial Five Years From Now (Box B&B 6)
        - 1967, Mar. 29, An American Looks at Color (Box B&B 6)
        - 1968, Mar., The Agency and the Company: We Can Live and Prosper Together, presentation before Procter & Gamble (Bonus, Cheer, Dash, Ivory Snow Liquid) (Box B&B 6)
        - 1968, May, An Analysis of Television Commercial Costs (Box B&B 6)
        - 1968, June, ANA-AAAA Clinic on Integration of Television Advertising (Box B&B 6)
        - 1972, The Television Commercial Five Years From Now (Box B&B 6)
        - 1974, The Life and Times of the American TV Commercial (Box B&B 6)
    - Staff Resources, 1939-1982, undated
      Includes manuals, leaflets, pamphlets, printed material, and lists created for reference or personal use by the employees of the company. Employee training; information for media specialists; lists of staff; employee activities; and management's ideas about employees' responsibilities to the company are documented in this subseries. The materials are grouped in four sections: Account Executives and Assistant Account Executives; Employee Information; Production, including General, Media, Television and Print; and Miscellaneous. Arranged chronologically within sections.
      - Account Executives and Assistant Account Executives (Box B&B 6)
        - 1979, Assistant Account Executive Group, Advertising Standards and Clearance Orientation (Box B&B 6)
        - 1979-1980, Summary of Client Accounting Systems and Procedures (Box B&B 6)
        - 1980, Some Practical Thoughts for the New Account Executive (Box B&B 6)
        - 1982, Assistant Account Executive Seminar, Broadcast Production (Box B&B 6)
        - 1982, Assistant Account Executive, Media Training Program, Phase II (Box B&B 6)
      - Employee Information
        - 1939, Client Contacts, Departments, and Staff Resumes (Box B&B 6)
        - 1945-1952, Employee Art Show (Box B&B 6)
        - 1950s-1979, Employee admonitions (Box B&B 6)
      - Employee Information (Box B&B 7)
        - 1954, 1980-1982, Personnel Lists (Box B&B 7)
        - 1956, About Benton & Bowles (Box B&B 7)
        - 1957, Welcome to Benton & Bowles (Box B&B 7)
        - circa 1962-1963, Conversation, A Periodic Talk with the People at Benton & Bowles (Box B&B 7)
        - 1972, Orientation Booklet (Box B&B 7)
        - 1977, undated, Business Ethics: Everyone's Responsibility (Box B&B 7)
        - 1978-1979, Benton & Bowles International: Agency Information Directory (Box B&B 7)
        - 1981-1983, Hobler Awards (Box B&B 7)
      - Production
        - General
          - 1975, Production Department (Box B&B 7)
          - 1983, Procedures for Commercial Broadcast Coordination (Box B&B 7)
        - Media Department
          - 1957, Media Fact Book (Box B&B 7)
          - 1969-1970, Media Management (Box B&B 7)
          - 1971, 1980, Media Guidelines (Box B&B 7)
          - 1982, Media Department Agenda (Box B&B 7)
          - undated, Media Planning (Box B&B 7)
          - undated, Test Market Planning/procedures (Box B&B 7)
      - Production (Box B&B 8)
        - Television and Print Production
          - 1965, Print Ad Control Department Manual (Box B&B 8)
          - 1978, Television and Print Production: Buying Methods (Box B&B 8)
          - 1981, Television Casting-Talent Contracts (Box B&B 8)
          - 1982, Television and Print Production: Print Control Department (Box B&B 8)
          - undated, Television and Print Production: The Three Main Elements of Print Advertising (Box B&B 8)
          - undated, Television and Print Production: TV/Radio Control Department, Summary and Procedures (Box B&B 8)
      - Miscellaneous
        - 1968, Suggested Program of Experimental Research, Advertising Research and Development (Box B&B 8)
        - circa 1970, Syndicated Market Data Services Purchased by Clients or Agency (Box B&B 8)
    - Recruitment, 1950s-1980s
      Materials prepared by Benton & Bowles to attract new employees to the company. Includes primarily printed material. Arranged chronologically.
      - circa 1959-1962, An Introduction to the Career Opportunities in Advertising- Marketing at Benton & Bowles (Box B&B 8)
      - 1959-1964, This Booklet is an Introduction to the Career Opportunities in Advertising-Marketing at Benton & Bowles (Box B&B 8)
      - 1950s[?], Career opportunities in Advertising and Marketing at Benton & Bowles (Box B&B 8)
      - 1966, advertisement for recruitment (Box B&B 8)
      - 1970s[?], Opportunities in Account Management at Benton & Bowles, Inc. (Box B&B 8)
      - 1980s[?], Benton & Bowles Recruitment Advertising (Box B&B 8)
  - Corporate Publications, 1938-1985 bulk 1940s-1985